So many devs are using LLM, but they
don't have the first idea about how
conversations with them actually work.
What is a user message? What is a system
prompt? What are tool calls? What are
reasoning tokens? Let's break it down.
Now, a simple conversation with an LLM
might look like this. You have user
messages, which are messages from you,
the user. And LLM messages are called
assistant messages. Now, in this
situation, we're just talking to the
bare model that the model provider gives
us. But if we want to customize the
LLM's behavior, then we can use a system
prompt. These are just messages at the
very start of the history which are
visible to the LLM, but usually not to
the user. And they're powerful, too. The
LLM, if there's a conflict between the
user and the system prompt, will usually
obey the system prompt. For instance, we
can tell it to respond in Morse code,
and then even if we say stop doing Morse
code, it will reply in Morse code. Of
course, this doesn't always work, and
there's plenty of examples of people
jailbreaking the system prompt, but this
is at least the theory. Lots of models
can send back reasoning tokens where the
model appears to think through its
output before it responds. These
reasoning tokens are just another part
of the assistant message. This is an
important concept here that messages can
contain multiple parts. This is useful
for file parts, too, where you can send
files to LLMs or like in image
generation use cases, you can get files
back from LLMs. For instance, here we're
sending a file to an LLM saying,
"Summarize this PDF." And it replies
with a summary. Finally, let's talk
about tools. With tools, you have the
ability to say, "You have access to a
write file tool to the LLM." This might
write a file to our file system or
something. Then the user is going to
say, "Write a to-do.md file." The
assistant then produces a tool call
message. That tool call has an ID on it.
And it also has an instruction to write
a file to-do.md with empty contents. Now
we in our applications take that tool
call and execute it and we send back to
the LLM a tool result with the same ID
as the tool call and the result of what
happened usually as a string. We get
back from the assistant a summary of
what happened wrote a to-do.md file
successfully. So tools are kind of like
a conversation between the LLM and our
system where the tool call is the LLM
asking us for something and the tool
result is us giving it the information
it needs. That's how AI powered apps
like claw code and cursor can do things
on your system. If you dig this, then
I've been sharing a lot of this stuff on
aihero.dev.